<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
	<herd>haskell</herd>
	<longdescription>
		/Usage/:
		
		@
		htsn [OPTIONS] [HOSTNAMES]
		@
		
		The Sports Network &lt;http://www.sportsnetwork.com/&gt; offers an XML feed
		containing various sports news and statistics. The goal of /htsn/
		is to watch the XML feed and parse the individual XML documents into
		files.
		
		Once started, we will choose an XML feed host to connect to. The
		choice is made from a list in a round-robin fashion, and by default,
		the list contains all known TSN feed hosts. Once we have a connection,
		your username and password are sent. If they are accepted, we begin to
		parse the feed saving all XML files to the configured output directory
		(see @--output-directory@).
		
		If we encounter an error (say, the connection is dropped), then we
		will attempt to connect to the next host in the list after waiting
		five seconds. This process continues indefinitely.
		
		The program can run either interactively (that is, outputting to the
		console), or as a daemon with the @--daemonize@ flag.
		
		/Input/:
		
		The program takes no input; a username and password must be supplied
		on the command-line or in a configuration file.
		
		/Output/:
		
		Output is not generated when running as a daemon; otherwise, standard
		out and standard error are fairly noisy. All traffic between /htsn/ and
		the feed server is displayed on stdout. Status messages are
		interspersed when they are generated with warnings and errors going to
		stderr. The following can be expected:
		
		* The only data we send to the feed are the username and password.
		These will be highlighted in green on stdout.
		
		* All data received from the feed will be echoed in the default color
		to stdout.
		
		* Informational messages will be highlighted in cyan and sent to stdout.
		
		* Warnings will be highlighted in yellow and sent to stderr.
		
		* Errors will be highlighted in red and sent to stderr.
		
		/Logging/:
		
		Logging is done either to syslog or a file. The destination and
		verbosity are controlled by the @--log-file@, @--log-level@,
		and @--syslog@ parameters which may be specified either on the command
		line or in the configuration file.
		
		/Options/:
		
		@
		\--daemonize, -d
		@
		
		Run as a daemon, in the background. When running as a daemon the
		\--pidfile, --run-as-group, and --run-as-user flags become relevant.
		
		Default: disabled
		
		@
		\--log-file
		@
		
		If you specify a file here, logs will be written to it (possibly in
		addition to syslog). Can be either a relative or absolute path. It
		will not be auto-rotated; use something log logrotate for that.
		
		Default: none
		
		@
		\--log-level
		@
		
		How verbose should the logs be? We log notifications at three levels:
		INFO, WARN, and ERROR. Specify the \&quot;most boring\&quot; level of
		notifications you would like to receive (in all-caps); more
		interesting notifications will be logged as well.
		
		Default: INFO
		
		@
		\--output-directory, -o
		@
		
		To which directory should we write the XML files?
		
		Default: .
		
		@
		\--password
		@
		
		The password associated with your TSN username. A password is
		required, so you must supply one either on the command line or in a
		configuration file.
		
		Default: none
		
		@
		\--pidfile
		@
		
		(Daemon mode only) Create a PID file in the given location. This is
		used by the init system on Unix to keep track of the running daemon.
		Its parent directory must be writable by the user/group that we will
		run as!
		
		Default: \/run\/htsn\/htsn.pid
		
		@
		\--run-as-group
		@
		
		(Daemon mode only) Run as the given system group. The PID file is
		written before privileges are dropped, so the only privileges needed
		by /htsn/ are those necessary to write the XML files and (optionally)
		the log file.
		
		Default: the current group
		
		@
		\--run-as-user
		@
		
		(Daemon mode only) Run as the given system user. The PID file is
		written before privileges are dropped, so the only privileges needed
		by /htsn/ are those necessary to write the XML files and (optionally)
		the log file.
		
		Default: the current user
		
		@
		\--syslog, -s
		@
		
		Enable logging to syslog. On Windows this will attempt to communicate
		(over UDP) with a syslog daemon on localhost, which will most likely
		not work.
		
		Default: disabled
		
		@
		\--username, -u
		@
		
		Your TSN username. A username is required, so you must supply one
		either on the command line or in a configuration file.
		
		Default: none
		
		/Feed Hosts/:
		
		It is possible to pass a list of feed hostnames on the command-line
		(see [HOSTNAMES] in the synopsis). By default /htsn/ will attempt
		to connect to every known TSN XML feed host in a round-robin fashion,
		so there is rarely a need to do this.
		
		/Configuration File/:
		
		Any of the command-line options mentioned above can be specified in a
		configuration file instead. We first look for \&quot;htsnrc\&quot; in the
		system configuration directory. We then look for a file named
		\&quot;.htsnrc\&quot; in the user&#39;s home directory. The latter will override
		the former.
		
		The user&#39;s home directory is simply $HOME on Unix; on Windows its
		wherever %APPDATA% points. The system configuration directory
		is determined by Cabal; the /sysconfdir/ parameter during
		the \&quot;configure\&quot; step is used.
		
		The file&#39;s syntax is given by examples in the htsnrc.example file
		(included with /htsn/).
		
		Options specified on the command-line override those in either
		configuration file.
	</longdescription>
</pkgmetadata>
